Taylor F. Ealy family papers, 1854-1937 (bulk 1874-1929)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Taylor F. Ealy family papers, 1854-1937 (bulk 1874-1929)
MS 162
Ealy, Taylor F. (Taylor Filmore), b. 1848
The collection contains letters, diaries, and writings of Taylor F. Ealy and members of his family.
.4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Taylor F. Ealy worked as a missionary, doctor, and teacher.
Organization
This collection is organized into four series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1874-1929
Series II: Diaries, 1854-1937
Series III: Writings, 1875-1889
Series IV: Photographs, 1865-1910
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains letters, diaries, and writings of Taylor F. Ealy and members of his family. Ealy operated the U.S. Freedmen's School for black children at Fort Arbuckle, Oklahoma, from 1874 to 1876. He lists pupils for August and September of 1875, and describes conditions at the time. In 1878, he relates their trip to Lincoln, New Mexico, as well as experiences during the Lincoln County War, while they held school and began a church. Writings by his wife, Mary, and daughter, Ruth, give their impressions of Billy the Kid. After moving to the Zuni Pueblo, Ealy describes life there in an 1879 diary. A diary from 1854-1856 by Henry B. Ealy, Taylor's first cousin and a minister in Pennsylvania is also present. Four diaries by Ruth Ealy describe a 1913 trip to Azores, North Africa, and Europe; a 1928 trip to Great Britain, and a 1937 trip to Japan. An undated typescript by her relates conditions of migrant farm workers' families in Tucson, Arizona. Photographs consist of six portraits of family members including Taylor and Mary Ealy.
Ealy, Taylor F. (Taylor Filmore), b. 1848 -- Archives; Ealy, Mary R; Ealy, Ruth Rea, 1877- -- Diaries; Billy, the Kid; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. -- Missions -- New Mexico; Frontier and pioneer life -- New Mexico -- Sources; Zuni Indians -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Lincoln County War, 1878 -- Personal narratives; Missionaries -- New Mexico -- Sources; Indians of North America -- New Mexico -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Migrant agricultural laborers -- Arizona; Freedmen -- Missions -- Indian Territory; Lincoln County (N.M.) -- History; New Mexico -- History -- 1848-; Fort Arbuckle; Correspondence; Diaries; Photographs
Related Material
Correspondence involving Mary R. Ealy is also located in the Maurice Fulton Papers (MS 57)
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1874-1929
  - Department of the Interior, Office of Indian Affairs, Edward P. Smith, Commissioner, to Taylor F. Ealy. November 3, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Presbyterian Committee of Missions for Freedmen. A. C. McClelland, to Taylor F. Ealy regarding the certificate of appointment of Miss Rebecca E. Forbes as teacher to replace Mrs. Lizzie D. Scott. March 17, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Presbyterian Committee of Missions for Freedmen. A. C. McClelland, to Taylor F. Ealy. August 18, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Taylor F. Ealy to: Dr. John C. Ealy (his father), Lincoln, NM. February 25, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Taylor F. Ealy to: Anna Clark Ealy (his mother), Lincoln, NM. March 1, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Taylor F. Ealy to: Corrie E. Ealy (his sister), Lincoln, NM. (Cover is postmarked Roswell, NM). March 4, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Taylor F. Ealy to: Mary, Lincoln, NM. March 4, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Taylor F. Ealy to: Albert E. Ealy (his brother), Lincoln, NM. March 13, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Taylor F. Ealy to: Anna Clark Ealy, Santa Fe, NM. August 3, 1878, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - M.S. Atterbury (for an unknown organization) to Mary R. Ealy. April 24, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Ladies Board of Missions (Julie M. Graham and Mrs. J. Dorimer), New York City, to Mary R. Ealy. April 24, 1879, December 1, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Susan E. Barber (McSween, nee Hummer), White Oaks, NM to Mary E. Ealy, (four letters). December 15, 1927 to September 12, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albert E. Ealy, Albuquerque, NM to: Brother. February 11, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albert E. Ealy, Albuquerque, NM to: Father (incomplete). April 25, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Diaries, 1854-1937
  - Diary of Henry B. Ealy (first cousin of Taylor F. Ealy); Pennsylvania and then Iowa. 1854-1856 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diary of Taylor Filmore Ealy; Zuni, New Mexico. 1879 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diary of Ruth R. Ealy (daughter of Taylor F. Ealy). 1913-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Trip to Azores, North Africa and Southern Europe, early July 1913.
    Europe, late July and August 1913.
    British Isles, July and August 1928.
    Japan, July and August 1937.
- Series III: Writings, 1875-1889
  - People and incidents at Fort Arbuckle, Indian Territory. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lincoln, New Mexico: "Frontier," a short piece on Lincoln and the trip there, by Taylor F. Ealy. March 11, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lincoln, New Mexico: the trip to Lincoln and an incident during the Lincoln County War, by Taylor F. Ealy. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lincoln, New Mexico: the trip to Lincoln, diary extracts from the Lincoln County War period with commentary, by Taylor F. Ealy. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lincoln, New Mexico: "The Lincoln County- War, New Mexico as I Saw It," by Taylor F. Ealy, (incomplete: pp. 1-21, 39). (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lincoln, New Mexico: "The Lincoln County- War, New Mexico as I Saw It," by Taylor F. Ealy, (complete version, copied by Mary R. Ealy). (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lincoln, New Mexico: the trip to and from Fort Stanton for the Dudley court of inquiry, by Taylor F. Ealy. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lincoln, New Mexico: notes on Billy the Kid, extracts from Pat Garrett's The Authentic Life of Billy the Kid, comments on principals of the Lincoln County War, by Taylor F. Ealy. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lincoln, New Mexico: "To the Rocky Mountain Presbyterian;" comments on the Lincoln County War, by Taylor F. Ealy. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The True Story of Billy the Kid," by Ruth R. Ealy; typescript which incorporates Billy the Kid's part in the Lincoln County War, "as my mother wrote it down for me several years ago." (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Zuni, New Mexico; Miscellaneous: "The old white mule," about an attempted trip from Zuni to Fort Wingate, by Taylor F. Ealy. June 26, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Zuni, New Mexico; Miscellaneous: map of locations between Zuni and Albuquerque. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Zuni, New Mexico; Miscellaneous: note of formation (proposed?) of an association for building a library, by Taylor F. Ealy, (incomplete). (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Zuni, New Mexico; Miscellaneous: "Migrants," by Ruth R. Ealy. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Photographs, 1865-1910
  - Photographs of the Ealy Family. 1865-1910 (Box 1, Folder 9)